<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>RSE at Sheffield</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/</link><description>RSE at Sheffield</description><atom:link href="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2018 10:58:22 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>SSI Fellowship success for Sheffield</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/SSI-2018/</link><dc:creator>Mike Croucher</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.software.ac.uk/"&gt;Software Sustainability Institute&lt;/a&gt;(SSI) is a cross-council funded group that supports the research software community in the UK. It has championed the role of the &lt;a href="http://rse.ac.uk/"&gt;Research Software Engineer&lt;/a&gt; and has led &lt;a href="https://www.software.ac.uk/index.php/blog/2017-04-10-state-nation-report-research-software-engineers-released"&gt;national&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://rse.ac.uk/rse-international-leaders-meeting/"&gt;international initiatives&lt;/a&gt; in the field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most popular activities undertaken by the SSI is their &lt;a href="https://www.software.ac.uk/fellowship-programme"&gt;fellowship program&lt;/a&gt;. This competitive process provides an &lt;a href="https://www.software.ac.uk/fellows"&gt;annual cohort of fellows&lt;/a&gt; with £3,000 to spend over fifteen months on a project of their choice.
Competition for these fellowships is fierce! Just like larger fellowships, applicants must get through a peer-reviewed application process that includes written proposals and selection days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am extremely happy to report that Sheffield has won, not just one, but &lt;strong&gt;three&lt;/strong&gt; SSI Fellowships this year. The only institution to match us was UCL, home of one of the first RSE group in the country.  Here's a brief statement from each Sheffield fellow explaining how they plan to use their funds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="background:#5F4B8B; display: inline-block; font-size:16px; padding: 1%;"&gt;

  &lt;div style="float:left; margin-left: 1%; padding: 0.25% 0;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://software.ac.uk/sites/default/files/inline-images/Tania-Allard.jpg" width="200px"&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;font color="white"&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt; Tania Allard &lt;/strong&gt;
  &lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;
  Nowadays, the majority of research relies on software to some degree. However, in many cases, there is little focus on developing scientific software using best development practices due to a number of reasons such as the lack of adequate mentoring and training, little understanding of the requirements of the scientific code, and software being undervalued or not considered as a primary research output. This has changed over time with the emergence of RSEs (Research Software Engineers) just like myself.  But certainly not every university or institute has an RSE team, neither every discipline is represented in the current RSE community. I plan to use this fellowship to develop an RSE winter school covering not only technical skills but also some of the craftsmanship and soft skills needed when developing a significant amount of scientific code. Also, this winter school will help to diversify the RSE pool by focusing on underrepresented groups within the community (e.g. gender, age, scientific disciplines, universities without RSEs) while disseminating
  best software practices among a number of disciplines.
  &lt;/font&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="background:#BFC8E0; display: inline-block; font-size:16px; padding: 1% 0;
padding-left: 1%;"&gt;

  &lt;div style="float:right; margin-left:1%; padding: 0.25% 0; padding-bottom: 0.1%!important;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://software.ac.uk/sites/default/files/inline-images/Becky-Arnold.jpg" width="200px"&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt; Becky Arnold &lt;/strong&gt;
  &lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;
  I'm planning use the fellowship funds to bring external speakers in to talk to the astrophysics group, with the goal of improving the style, efficiency and sustainability of our coding. As physicists, as I imagine in many fields, we are largely taught to code to get the things we need to be done completed as quickly as possible, with little regard for the quality of the code itself. We are taught how to code, but not how to code well. I want to give us the opportunity to improve in that. Also I hope to change the way we think about coding, from a disposable stepping stone used to further research as quickly as possible to a fundamental part of the science itself.

  &lt;/div&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="background:#255498; display: inline-block; font-size:16px; padding: 1%;"&gt;

  &lt;div style="float:left; margin-left:1%; padding: 0.25% 0;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://software.ac.uk/sites/default/files/inline-images/Adam-Tomkins.png" width="200px"&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;font color="white"&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;Adam Tomkins&lt;/strong&gt;
  &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
  I am part of the Fruit Fly Brain Observatory project, with the aim to open up neurological data to the community, in an accessible way. Part of the issue with open data sharing is the vast amount of custom storage and format solutions, used by different labs. With this fellowship, I will be holding training events for both biologists and computational modelers on how to use the latest open data standards, demonstrating how using open software can generate instant added-value to data, with a larger community of tools and platforms.
  &lt;/font&gt;   

  &lt;/div&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;RSE at Sheffield&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we set up the Sheffield RSE group, one of our aims was to help cultivate an environment at Sheffield where research software was valued. We do this by providing &lt;a href="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/training/"&gt;training events&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/linuistics_grant_2016/"&gt;writing grants with academics&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/testimonials/"&gt;consulting with researchers to improve software&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/intel-R-iceberg/"&gt;improving the HPC environment&lt;/a&gt; and anything else we can think of.  Of course, correlation does not imply causation but we like to believe that we helped our new SSI Fellows in some way (&lt;a href="https://www.software.ac.uk/blog/2017-12-08-welcome-software-sustainability-institute-fellows-2018"&gt;the SSI agrees&lt;/a&gt;) and we are very happy to bask in their reflected glory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/SSI-2018/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 Feb 2018 17:47:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Code in the Academy: Rebecca Senior</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/code-in-the-academy-rebecca-senior/</link><dc:creator>Anna Krystalli</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;h4&gt;In this interview series, the RSE team talk to University of Sheffield students about the role of coding in their research.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div style="background:#CADEBF; display: inline-block; font-size:16px; padding: 1% 0;"&gt;

  &lt;div style="float:left; margin-left:1%; padding: 0.25% 0;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/images/Rebecca_A_Senior.JPG" width="200px" style="border: 5px solid teal;"&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;div style="vertical-align: middle; padding: 5% 1%;"&gt;

  In out first of the series, we speak to &lt;strong&gt;Rebecca Senior&lt;/strong&gt;.

  &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;

  She's in the final year of her PhD in the &lt;strong&gt;Department of Animal and Plant Sciences&lt;/strong&gt; studying the &lt;strong&gt;interactions between land-use and climate change in tropical rainforests and what this means for biodiversity conservation&lt;/strong&gt;. She's currently looking into how deforestation affects forest connectivity, so lots of spatial analyses. She mainly codes in R but also I dabbles in a bit of Python.

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How did you first get into coding?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;em&gt;What motivated you to learn? How and what did you start learning?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was an undergrad we did our statistics in R commander, which is a GUI (Graphical User Interface) for R. A supervisor wisely told me that there’d come a point when I couldn’t do what I needed using R commander alone, so I spent the summer before my final year grappling with R and cursing it profusely until I was somewhat competent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What are your favourite coding tools?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m pretty in love with the R + RStudio + tidyverse combo. RStudio is an integrated development environment (IDE) for R, which basically makes coding look far less hideous, and which allows you to write, save and run code in a more efficient way. The tidyverse is “an opinionated collection of R packages designed for data science”. The various packages make data management/analysis/presentation much more intuitive for many people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How do you think coding has helped you in your work?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For one thing it got me an internship at UNEP-WCMC (UN Environment World Conservation Monitoring Centre) after I finished my undergrad, and it subsequently helped me to get this PhD position! More fundamentally, coding has sped things up, enhanced the reproducibility of my work and my ability to collaborate with others, and has helped me tackle complex problems that I couldn’t have done manually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Tell us about your favourite coding achievement.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote a teeny R package to estimate the time of sunrise and sunset based on date and location. It’s actually a really simple implementation of &lt;a href="https://www.esrl.noaa.gov/gmd/grad/solcalc/calcdetails.html"&gt;solar calculations developed by NOAA for MS Excel&lt;/a&gt;, but it was instrumental to one of my thesis chapters and it was my first experience of making an R package. Check it out here: &lt;a href="https://github.com/rasenior/SolarCalc"&gt;https://github.com/rasenior/SolarCalc&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How do you think these skills can be better supported in academia?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since all researchers (students and supervisors alike) are judged primarily on their publication output, encouraging students to publish software would be an obvious place to start. In my field, the journal Methods in Ecology and Evolution is a very popular option for people seeking to publish R packages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, not all coding results in something publishable and, in any case, the sharing of software via peer-reviewed publications is not always a good measure of its usefulness anyway. I think students should be encouraged to share their coding achievements with peers, and more broadly via online platforms such as GitHub and Gist. Software has made its way into academic impact reporting, so perhaps coding should also be more valued within progress reports and theses?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be great to see the teaching of coding broaden beyond statistics, especially within the life sciences. There is so much more to coding than conducting t-tests! With continuing advances in technology we have to grapple with much bigger and more varied datasets, analyse them in sometimes very complex ways, and present the methods and results in a clear and succinct format, all the while maintaining reproducibility as much as possible. That’s a whole heap of coding skills that are very infrequently taught!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How do you see coding fitting in with your future career?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether I stay in academia or not, I will continue coding. I hope that my coding skills will help me secure a research position post-PhD. I’m not sure yet exactly where my research will take me, but I hope it involves developing R packages and making pretty figures in ggplot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Any coding advice for new PhD students?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t be afraid to set aside time for learning something new. Learning takes time – accept that and incorporate it into your work schedule. You’re still a student and some of the skills you learn may open doors you didn’t even know were there.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>RSE Interview Series</category><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/code-in-the-academy-rebecca-senior/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Feb 2018 08:09:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>CodeFirstGirls meets Hacktoberfest</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/codefirstgirls-meets-hacktoberfest/</link><dc:creator>Tania A.</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div style="width: 90%;
        height: auto;
        margin: 30px;
    text-align:center;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/images/CFG_AW1.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is that time of the year again! The autumn-winter courses for
&lt;a href="http://www.codefirstgirls.org.uk/"&gt;CodeFirst: girls&lt;/a&gt;
are in full swing at Sheffield, Manchester and many other locations all
 over the UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the lead instructor of the Python courses part of my 'job' is to make sure
that everything runs smoothly and that the gals make the most of the course.
Since the courses run only over 8 weeks and we have loads of ground to cover I decided to
improve the way the instructors communicate and plan the course as well as how we deliver the
contents for the course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Implementation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are some of the approaches we are currently using in our courses:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GitHub&lt;/strong&gt;: I use Git and GitHub all the time for all my projects and tasks. So it only made sense to make it a central point of contact as well as the main place for all the additional material to be kept into. It has worked wonders, all of the organisation stuff is there, we make sure that the additional materials developed by us are peer-reviewed and it makes it makes all of our lives easier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GitKraken&lt;/strong&gt;: ok ok I know many people would prefer teaching Git using the command line, but I have used both command line and GUI approaches and I think you first need to know your audience to better understand which approach to use. In this case GitKraken was my weapon of choice... powerful, intuitive, it can be easily integrated with GitHub, BitBucket and GitLab, and did I say beautiful? Yes, which makes it suitable for visual learners.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learning by doing&lt;/strong&gt;: I am a firm believer of learning by doing. It sometimes is the best approach to get the grips of things. How do you make the git-add-commit-push workflow a natural habit? Exactly, by doing it over and over again. So we are making sure that every session would include bits and pieces where the gals had to generate pieces of code, push them to their repos, collaborate with others and or create pull requests.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feedback on the fly&lt;/strong&gt;: As a Sofware/Data carpentry intructor some of the things I love the most is the use of post-its. That way you and the helpers know straight away who is struggling (red post-it) and how is not (green post-it) that way the learners get help instantly and the main instructor gets visual clues on how fast or slow to proceed. At the end of the day the learners write on the post-its something they liked or learned and something that could be improved or that they struggled with. So I decided to give this a go at CFG and so it has helped us a lot so far.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Active engagement&lt;/strong&gt;: one of the key things that makes initiatives such as CodeFirstGirls work is not the fact that we teach them how to code, online courses do that. But the whole thing is an excellent community building activity, the gals find common minded people, are exposed to role models, and feel empowered to continue their career in tech. That is the beauty of what we do. So it is only fair that we engage with them. We have our own #hashtag (Go now and look for #ShefCodeFirst in Twitter), we have guest speakers, slack channels, &lt;a href="http://bitsandchips.me/Shef_CodeFirst_Python/"&gt;our very own course website&lt;/a&gt; (obvs in GitHub pages) and we try to open their eyes to the wider tech and open source community. Also we have many Octocat stickers to give away!!!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div style="width: 70%;
        height: auto;
        margin: 0 auto;
    text-align:center;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/images/CFG_AW2.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Hacktoberfest&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mentioned before that we try to keep the gals actively engaged throughout the course as well as to integrate them to the wider community.
And what a better way to do this but getting the gals involved in &lt;a href="https://hacktoberfest.digitalocean.com/"&gt;Hacktoberfest&lt;/a&gt;!!! We ere a bit tight on time but I thought it was worth trying to get some of the girls involved in something like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="width: 70%;
        height:400px;
        margin: 20px auto;
    text-align:center;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/images/hacktoberfest.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By doing so the girls would get the following benefits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn how to contribute to open source projects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integrate to the open source community&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get extra coding practice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get extra git practice (4 Pull Requests were needed to complete this)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If completed they would get a special edition t-shirt (Whoop whoop)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That meant extra work for me: find specific tasks and projects for them to contribute to, merge pull requests bonanza, and prepare extra gifs and guides on how to complete the tasks.
But it was totally worth it!!! I was more than delighted to see all the PR coming into our own repo as well as getting all the notifications from the girls getting involved in Hacktoberfest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know not everyone got involved as many have PhDs, Master's, dissertations, and a life to look after.
But I am massively proud of them all. So many of our gals had never used Git or GitHub before and now they
are collaborating like pros.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="width: 45%;
        height: auto;
        margin: 20px auto;
    text-align:center;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/images/PR_bonanza.png"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talk about motivation :) And if you want to keep up to date with the end of course projects they will be presenting in 5 weeks time keep an eye on Twitter!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/codefirstgirls-meets-hacktoberfest/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2018 13:31:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>ReproHacking at Opencon London 2017 Doathon</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/opencon_london/</link><dc:creator>Anna Krystalli</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://d3n8a8pro7vhmx.cloudfront.net/righttoresearch/pages/1462/features/original/OpenCon_2017_London_-_NB_Banner.png?1505763567"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building on the success of last year’s &lt;a href="https://annakrystalli.shinyapps.io/OpenConBerlin_reprohack/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;#Reprohack2016&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for the Berlin OpenCon satellite event, I rejoined the team of organisers (&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/laurawheelers"&gt;Laura Wheeler&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Protohedgehog"&gt;Jon Tennant&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/tonyR_H"&gt;Tony Ross-Hellauer&lt;/a&gt; ) and teamed up with &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/PeterKraker?ref_src=twsrc%5Egoogle%7Ctwcamp%5Eserp%7Ctwgr%5Eauthor"&gt;Peter Kraker&lt;/a&gt; to develop the hackday for this year’s &lt;a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/opencon-london-2017-open-for-what-tickets-38036414941#"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OpenCon London 2017&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To allow better reflection on this year's theme, “Open for what?”, we expanded the format to two tracks, opening up the scope for both projects and participants. &lt;strong&gt;One track retained the ReproHack format from last year, the other, a broader track, offered the opportunity for leads of any type of open science project to &lt;a href="https://annakrystalli.shinyapps.io/OpenConLondon_Doathon/"&gt;submit them for work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Projects were not constrained to coding and you didn't have to code to take part in the session - anyone with an interest in creative contribution to open science in whichever capacity was welcome. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the day, after a round of introductions and sharing our motivations for attending, we reviewed the submissions and knuckled down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;ReproHacking&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original ReproHack was inspired by &lt;strong&gt;Owen Petchey’s &lt;a href="https://github.com/opetchey/RREEBES"&gt;Reproducible Research in Ecology, Evolution, Behaviour, and Environmental Studies course&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, where students attempt to reproduce the analysis and figures of a paper from the raw data, so we wanted to attempt the same. They take a few months over a number of sessions though, so, given our time constraints, we focused on reproducing papers that have also published the code behind them. This year we had a whole day, which gave us more time to dig deeper into the materials, moving beyond evaluating them for reproducibility, to how understandable, even how reusable they were. While fewer, we still had some &lt;a href="https://annakrystalli.shinyapps.io/OpenConLondon_Doathon/"&gt;excellent submissions&lt;/a&gt; to choose from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I'm pleased to report that two of the three papers attempted were succesfully reproduced!&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;***&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was particulalrly impressed with the paper &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/andrewajube/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Andrew Ajube&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; tackled: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://peerj.com/preprints/3119/"&gt;The State of OA: A large-scale analysis of the prevalence and impact of Open Access articles&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Piwowar et. al&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Successfully reproduced our results earlier thanks to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/annakrystalli?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@annakrystalli&lt;/a&gt; and Andrew, and just now mentioned in &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/catmacOA?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@catmacOA&lt;/a&gt;'s talk. &lt;a href="https://t.co/qkaOTySt7W"&gt;https://t.co/qkaOTySt7W&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/OpenCon?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#OpenCon&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/ymVoydy93p"&gt;pic.twitter.com/ymVoydy93p&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Lisa Matthias (@l_matthia) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/l_matthia/status/933070982025240576?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;November 21, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under very minimal supervision and never having used R or Rstudio before, he managed to reproduce &lt;strong&gt;an analysis in an rmarkdown &lt;a href="http://r-pkgs.had.co.nz/vignettes.html"&gt;vignette&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;]. I think this speaks volumes, to the power of the tools and approaches we have freely available to us, of following best practice (well described in this epic Jenny Bryan &lt;a href="https://www.tidyverse.org/articles/2017/12/workflow-vs-script/"&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;strong&gt;project-oriented workflows&lt;/strong&gt;), the effort the producers went to, and of course, genuine engagement by Andrew. It can work and it is rewarding!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Let it be known that Andrew Ajube, the participant that reproduced it had never used &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/rstudio?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@rstudio&lt;/a&gt; or rmd before but still managed to reproduce it w/ only minimal guidance from me. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Kudos to you the producers! &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/OpenConLondon?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#OpenConLondon&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ReproHack17?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#ReproHack17&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/4WE2cXOetn"&gt;https://t.co/4WE2cXOetn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— annakrystalli (@annakrystalli) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/annakrystalli/status/933075390154887169?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;November 21, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;***&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I worked with &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mariosge90?lang=en"&gt;Marios Andreou&lt;/a&gt; on a very well curated paper, submitted by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/benmarwick?lang=en"&gt;Ben Marwick&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0047248415000846?via%3Dihub"&gt;The archaeology, chronology and stratigraphy of Madjedbebe (Malakunanja II): a site in northern Australia with early occupation&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Clarkson et. al&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper offered two options to reproduce the work. A completely self-contained archive version in a docker container, which Marios spun up and reproduced the analysis in, in no time. I opted for the second option, &lt;a href="https://rmflight.github.io/posts/2014/07/analyses_as_packages.html"&gt;installing the analysis as a package&lt;/a&gt;. It did require a bit of manual dependency managing but, this was documenteted in the &lt;a href="https://github.com/benmarwick/1989-excavation-report-Madjedbebe"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;analysis repository README&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on github. This meant that all functionality developed for the analysis was available for me to explore. Presenting the &lt;a href="https://github.com/benmarwick/1989-excavation-report-Madjedbebe/blob/master/vignettes/analysis-of-dates-lithics-shell-from-1989-excavations.Rmd"&gt;analysis in a vignette&lt;/a&gt; also made it’s inner working much more penetrable and allowed us to &lt;a href="https://opencon-london.github.io/OpenCon_London-Doathon/marwick_archaelogy_repro/analysis-of-dates-lithics-shell-from-1989-excavations.nb.html"&gt;interactively edit it to get a better feel of the data&lt;/a&gt; and how the analysis functions worked. Ultimately, not only could we reproduce the science in the paper (open for transparency), we could also satisfy ourselves with what the code was doing (open for robustness) and reuse the code (open for resuse). The only step further would be to make the functionality more generalisable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Woah! Successful double reproduction at &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/OpenCon?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#OpenCon&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Scrumblebee?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@Scrumblebee&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/annakrystalli?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@annakrystalli&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mariosge90?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@mariosge90&lt;/a&gt; congrats!! &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/openbiscuits?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#openbiscuits&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/9Wp4AsFevz"&gt;pic.twitter.com/9Wp4AsFevz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Jon Tennant (@Protohedgehog) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Protohedgehog/status/932969845242695685?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;November 21, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the session we collected some feedback about the experience, reflecting on reproducibility, the tools and approaches used, documentation and reusability. Here's the &lt;a href="https://github.com/annakrystalli/write-ups/blob/master/assets/OpenCon_ReproHack%20feedback_form.pdf"&gt;feedback we had for Ben's work&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As calls for openness are maturing, it's good to push beyond why open? to indeed, open how? open when? open for what? Different approaches to &lt;strong&gt;how&lt;/strong&gt; a study is made "reproducible" has implications on &lt;strong&gt;what&lt;/strong&gt; the openness can achieve downstream. It's probably a good time to start clarifying the remit of different approaches. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Do-athoning&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the do-athon side there were a couple of cool projects. Peter and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/40_thieves?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&amp;amp;ref_url=http%3A%2F%2F127.0.0.1%3A46498%2Frmd_output%2F1%2F"&gt;Ali Smith&lt;/a&gt; worked on &lt;strong&gt;Visual data discovery in Open Knowledge Maps&lt;/strong&gt;,  adapting their knowledge mapping framework, Head Start, to the specific requirements of data discovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;We're trying an agile approach to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/OpenConLondon?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#OpenConLondon&lt;/a&gt; hack! First feedback session.&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/40_thieves?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@40_thieves&lt;/a&gt; talking us through work on their &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/openscience?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#openscience&lt;/a&gt; project, adapting &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/OK_Maps?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@OK_Maps&lt;/a&gt; approach to dataset search! &lt;a href="https://t.co/TPk12yejzF"&gt;pic.twitter.com/TPk12yejzF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— annakrystalli (@annakrystalli) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/annakrystalli/status/932945063365300224?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;November 21, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tony, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/l_matthia"&gt;Lisa Mattias&lt;/a&gt; and Jon continued work on the, open to anyone, hyper-collaborative drafting of the &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1un3N3JsvfodSxW3FMAoOMHaESPMzJSBr7kcrxWjoEnE/edit#"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;"Foundations for Open Science Strategy Development"&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; document, started at the &lt;a href="https://github.com/sparcopen/doathon/issues/24"&gt;OpenCon 2017 Do-athon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Agile hacking&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I love about hacks is that you never know quite what skills you’re gonna get in the room. In our case, we got scrumaster &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/sven-ihnken-4153b525/"&gt;Sven Ihnken&lt;/a&gt; offering to help us navigate the day. We’ve actually been agile working for the passed few months with the nascent shef dataviz team and I find it a productive way to work. So an agile hack seemed a worthy experiment. I personally thought it worked really well. It was nice to split up the day into shorter sprints and review progress around the room half way. And Sven did do a great job “buzzing” around the room, keeping us focused and engaged and ultimately, getting all our tasks from doing to done!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;***&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, we shared what we'd worked on, and settled in for the main Opencon London evening event. As the event talks went through more traditional remits of OpenCon, from public engagement to open access to literature and data, it just reiterated to me that each strand of openness is yet another way to invite people in to science. For me, inviting people all the way in, into your code and data, your entire workflow, is the bravest and most rewarding of all!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/opencon_london/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 21 Dec 2017 08:09:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A successful 2nd RSE conference</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/a-successful-2nd-rse-conference/</link><dc:creator>Tania A.</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;h2&gt;RSE Sheffield in the 2nd RSE conference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/images/RSE17.jpg" alt="RSE17"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second RSE conference took place on the 7th and 8th of September 2017 at the
Museum of Science and Industry &lt;a href="https://www.msimanchester.org.uk/"&gt;MOSI&lt;/a&gt;.
There were over 200 attendees, 40 talks, 15  workshops,
3 keynote talks, one of which was given by our very own head honcho Mike Croucher
(slides &lt;a href="https://mikecroucher.github.io/RSE_2017_keynote_presentation/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), and geeky chats galore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RSE team members &lt;a href="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/a-successful-2nd-rse-conference/mkchimeh.com"&gt;Mozhgan&lt;/a&gt; and Tania were involved in the organising committee as talks co-chairs and diversity chair (disclose: they had nothing to do with Mike's keynote). Also, all of the RSE Sheffield team members made it to the conference, which seems to be a first due to the diverse commitments and project involvement of all of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once again, the event was a huge success thanks to the efforts of the committee and volunteers as well as the amazing RSE community that made this a en engaging and welcoming event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conference highlights&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With so many parallel sessions, workshops, and chats happening all at the same time it is quite complicated to keep a track of every single thing going on. And it seems rather unlikely that this will change over time as it was &lt;strong&gt;evident&lt;/strong&gt; that the RSE community has outgrown the current conference size.
So we decided to highlight our favourites of the event:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talk on 'Imposter syndrome' by Vijay Sharma: Who in the scientific community has not ever experienced this? Exactly! So when given the chance everyone jumped into this talk full of relatable stories and handy tips on how to get over it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another talk that seemed to have gathered loads of interest was that of
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/tbyhdgs"&gt;Toby Hodges&lt;/a&gt; from  EMBL on community building. This came as no surprise (at least to me) as RSEs often act as community builders or as a bridge between collaborating communities. Opposed to &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; being focused on developing software and pushing it into production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the first day the RSEs had the chance to have a go at interacting with the &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-gb/hololens"&gt;Microsoft Hololens&lt;/a&gt;. There was a considerable queue to have a go at this, and unfortunately, we were not among the chosen ones to play with this. Maybe in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My hands-on workshop on 'Jupyter notebooks for reproducible research'. I was ecstatic to know the community found this workshop interesting and had to run this twice!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, I'd like to casually throw in here that I have been elected as a committee member for the UK RSE association, so expect to read more about this in this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For obvious reasons I missed most of the workshops but Kenji Takeda's workshop on 'Learn how to become an AI Super-RSE' was another favourite of the delegates as this was run twice too!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Our workshop on Jupyter notebooks for reproducible research&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a RSE means that I serve as an advocate of sustainable software development. Also, as I have discussed here before: I am greatly concerned about reproducibility and replicability in science.
Which, I might add, is not an easy task to embark onto.
Thankfully, there are loads of tools and practices that we can adopt as part of our workflows to ensure that the code we develop is done by following the best practices possible, and as a consequence, can support science accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, as members of the community come up with more refined and powerful tools in the realm of scientific computing we (the users and other developers) adopt some of those tools meaning that we often end up modifying our workflows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such is the case of Jupyter notebooks. They brought up to life a whole new era of literate programming: where scientist, students, data scientist, and aficionados can share their scripts in a human readable format. What is more important, they transform scripts into a conveying scientific narrative where functions and loops are followed by their graphical outputs or allow the user to interact via widgets. This ability to openly share whole analysis pipelines is for sure, a step in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the adoption of tools like this  brings not only a number of advantages but also presents a number of challenges and integration issues with previously developed tools.
For example, the traditional version control tools (including diff and merge tools) do not play nicely with the notebooks. Also, the notebooks have to be tested as any other piece of code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the workshop, I introduced two tools: &lt;a href="https://github.com/jupyter/nbdime"&gt;nbdime&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/computationalmodelling/nbval"&gt;nbval&lt;/a&gt;, which were developed as part of the European funded project: &lt;a href="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/a-successful-2nd-rse-conference/www.opendreamkit.org"&gt;OpenDreamKit&lt;/a&gt;. Such tools introduce very much needed version control and validation capabilities to the Jupyter notebooks, addressing some of the issues mentioned before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in order to cover these tools as well as how you would integrate them within your
workflow I divided the workshop in three parts: diffing and merging of the notebooks, notebooks validation, and a brief 101 on reproducibility practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Notebooks diffing and merging&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the first part of the workshop the attendees shared their experiences using traditional version control tools with Jupyter notebooks... unsurprisingly everyone had had terrible experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then all of them had some hands-on time on how to use nbdime for diffing and merging from the command line as well as from their rich html rendered version (completely offline).
As we progressed with the tutorial I could see some happy faces around the room and they all agreed that this was much needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Need more convincing? This tweet showed up in my feed just this week
And just earlier this week this tweet showed up on my feed:
&lt;img src="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/images/tweet-nbdime.PNG" width="500px"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Notebooks validation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second part of the workshop focused on the validation of the notebooks. And here I would like to ask this first: &lt;em&gt;'How many of you have found an amazing notebook somewhere in the web just to clone it and find out that it just does not work: dependencies are broken, functions are deprecated, can't tell if the results are reproducible?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can tell you, we have all been there. And in such cases nbval is your best friend. It is a &lt;strong&gt;py.test&lt;/strong&gt; plugin to determine whether execution of the stored inputs match the stored outputs of the &lt;code&gt;.ipynb&lt;/code&gt; file. Whilst also ensuring that the notebooks are running without errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This lead to an incredible discussion on its place within conventional testing approaches. Certainly, it does not replace unittesting or integration testing, but it could be seen as a form of &lt;em&gt;regression&lt;/em&gt; testing for the notebooks. Want to make sure that your awesome documentation
formed by Jupyter notebooks is still working in a few months time? Why not use CI and nbval?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Wrapping up&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The closing to the workshop was a 101 on working towards reproducible scientific computing. We shared some of our approaches for reproducible workflows and encouraged the delegates to share theirs. We covered topics such as valuing your digital assets, licensing, automation, version control and continuous integration, among others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The perfect close to a great RSE conference!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Just a few more things&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me highlight that all the materials for the workshop can be found at: &lt;a href="https://github.com/trallard/JNB_reproducible"&gt;https://github.com/trallard/JNB_reproducible&lt;/a&gt; and that all of it is completely self contained in the form of a Docker container.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you missed out on the conference and would like to see the videos and slides of the various talks do not forget to visit the &lt;a href="http://rse.ac.uk/conf2017/talk-slides-downloads/"&gt;RSE conference website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/a-successful-2nd-rse-conference/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2017 14:46:35 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Iceberg vs ShARC</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/iceberg-vs-sharc/</link><dc:creator>Mike Croucher</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TL;DR Around 100 of Iceberg's nodes are ancient and weaker than a decent laptop. You may get better performance by switching to ShARC.  You'll get even better performance by investing in the &lt;a href="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/resources/hpc/premium-hpc/"&gt;RSE project on ShARC&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Benchmarking different nodes on our HPC systems&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been benchmarking various nodes on Iceberg and ShARC using Matrix-Matrix multiplication.
This operation is highly parallel and optimised these days and is also a vital operation in many scientific workflows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The benchmark units are GigaFlops (Billion operations per second) and &lt;strong&gt;higher is better&lt;/strong&gt;
Here are the results for maximum matrix sizes of 10000 by 10000, sorted worst to best&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/mikecroucher/Jupyter-Matrix-Matrix/blob/master/results/Sheffield_iceberg_12cores.ipynb"&gt;119 GigaFlops&lt;/a&gt; - Old Iceberg 'Westmere' Nodes (12 core X5650 CPUs )&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/mikecroucher/Jupyter-Matrix-Matrix/blob/master/results/MacBookPro2014.ipynb"&gt;169 Gigaflops&lt;/a&gt; - My 4 core Mid-2014 MacBook Pro&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/mikecroucher/Jupyter-Matrix-Matrix/blob/master/results/Sheffield_iceberg_16cores.ipynb"&gt;333 Gigaflops&lt;/a&gt; - New Iceberg 'Ivy Bridge' Nodes (16 core )&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/mikecroucher/Jupyter-Matrix-Matrix/blob/master/results/Sheffield_sharc_16cores.ipynb"&gt;458 Gigaflops&lt;/a&gt; - Standard ShARC node (16 cores)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/mikecroucher/Jupyter-Matrix-Matrix/blob/master/results/Sheffield_sharc_32cores.ipynb"&gt;802 Gigaflops&lt;/a&gt; - 32 core ShARC node (only available to &lt;a href="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/resources/hpc/premium-hpc/"&gt;RSE queue contributors&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the &lt;a href="http://docs.hpc.shef.ac.uk/en/latest/iceberg/cluster_specs.html"&gt;Iceberg cluster specs&lt;/a&gt;, over half of Iceberg is made up of the old 'Westmere' nodes.  According to these benchmarks, these are almost &lt;strong&gt;4 times slower&lt;/strong&gt; than a standard node on ShARC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The RSE project - the fastest nodes available&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We in the RSE group have co-invested with our collaborators in additional hardware on ShARC to form a 'Premium queue'.  This hardware includes large memory nodes (&lt;strong&gt;768 Gigabytes per node&lt;/strong&gt; - 12 times the amount that's normally available), Advanced GPUs (&lt;a href="https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/data-center/dgx-1/"&gt;A DGX-1 server&lt;/a&gt;) and 'dense-core' nodes with 32 CPUs each.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These 32 core nodes are capable of &lt;a href="https://github.com/mikecroucher/Jupyter-Matrix-Matrix/blob/master/results/Sheffield_sharc_32cores.ipynb"&gt;over 800 Gigaflops&lt;/a&gt; and so are 6.7 times faster than the old Iceberg nodes.  Furthermore, since they are only available to contributors, the queues will be shorter too!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Details of how to participate in the RSE-queue experiment on ShARC can be &lt;a href="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/resources/hpc/premium-hpc/"&gt;found on our website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What if ShARC is slower than Iceberg?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These benchmarks give reproducible evidence that ShARC can be significantly faster than Iceberg when well-optimised code is used.  We have heard some unconfirmed reports that code run on ShARC can be slower than code run on Iceberg.  If this is the case for you, please &lt;a href="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/contact/"&gt;get in touch with us&lt;/a&gt; and give details.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/iceberg-vs-sharc/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 23 Nov 2017 13:04:27 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Sheffield R Users group celebrates Hacktoberfest</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/sheffieldR-hacktoberfest/</link><dc:creator>Anna Krystalli</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We'll be honest here and say that our &lt;a href="http://sheffieldr.github.io/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sheffield R Users group&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Hacktoberfest celebrations&lt;/strong&gt; started as a last minute stroke of inspiration. Nearing our standard first Tuesday of the month meetup, our speaker lineup for October was thin. At the same time I'd spent the last month mentoring as part of &lt;a href="https://mozilla.github.io/leadership-training/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mozilla Open Leadership program&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; again, which was gearing up to have projects participate in &lt;a href="https://hacktoberfest.digitalocean.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hacktoberfest&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;a global month long celebration of open source&lt;/strong&gt;, organised by &lt;a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Digital Ocean&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and designed to get people engaged with projects hosted openly on &lt;a href="https://github.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GitHub&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. For those unfamiliar with the platform, GitHub is one of many code repositories where open projects live allowing anyone to copy, modify and even contribute back to open source projects, many of which depend on such volunteer contributions. As it takes a village to raise a child so it takes a small village to build, maintain, continue to develop and support the users of a succesful open source project, where even small non-technical contributions, for example, to documentation, can be a huge help to maintainers (see Yihui Xie's (of &lt;code&gt;knitr&lt;/code&gt; fame) &lt;a href="https://yihui.name/en/2017/10/thanks-claus/"&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; on this). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what better way to entice folks to get involved than the promise of &lt;strong&gt;stickers and a free t-shirt on completion of the Hacktoberfest challenge!&lt;/strong&gt; And the challenge? Simple. &lt;strong&gt;Make four contributions&lt;/strong&gt; (pull requests) to any open source project on GitHub between the 1st and 31st of October. And the contribution can be anything — fixing bugs, creating new features, or updating and writing documentation. Game on!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many project owners had labelled specific issues up and we noticed there were many &lt;a href="https://ropensci.org/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;rOpenSci projects&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in need of some &lt;a href="https://github.com/search?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;amp;q=label%3Ahacktoberfest+state%3Aopen+type%3Aissue+language%3AR&amp;amp;type="&gt;&lt;strong&gt;#rstats&lt;/strong&gt; help&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Some &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Hacktoberfest?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#Hacktoberfest&lt;/a&gt; issues in `skimr` appropriate for first-timers: &lt;a href="https://t.co/zNjMVUkRjP"&gt;https://t.co/zNjMVUkRjP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;About skimr: &lt;a href="https://t.co/3cWXgkjLuz"&gt;https://t.co/3cWXgkjLuz&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/bxVSEtFLXT"&gt;https://t.co/bxVSEtFLXT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— rOpenSci (@rOpenSci) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/rOpenSci/status/919941004144271361?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;October 16, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that &lt;strong&gt;doing is the best way to learn&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;working on problems outside our daily routines can be a great distraction&lt;/strong&gt;, we thought it'd be a great idea to skip the standard talk meetup format for October and instead opt for some &lt;strong&gt;hands on Hacktoberfest action!&lt;/strong&gt; It would also give the opportunity to any of our R users who were curious but did not have previous experience with GitHub and open source to learn more through practice and also in a friendly space where they could get help with any questions or uncertainties. Working the details through on Twitter (as you do!), an exciting plan emerged...not only would we extend to holding weekly sessions throughout the whole month, we would &lt;strong&gt;end with a special Halloween celebratory session!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;We can have &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt; pumpkin if it doesn't violate safety regulations.&lt;/p&gt;— Raniere Silva (@rgaiacs) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/rgaiacs/status/915147378361061376?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;October 3, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Kick off meetup - briefing session&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the kick off meetup, fellow Sheffield R Users Group co-organisers &lt;strong&gt;Tamora James&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/soayipm"&gt;\@soaypim&lt;/a&gt;) and &lt;strong&gt;Mathew Hall&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mathew_hall"&gt;\@mathew_hall&lt;/a&gt;) introduced participants to &lt;strong&gt;the general ideas and principles of open source&lt;/strong&gt;, discussed &lt;strong&gt;contibuting to open projects&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;introduced GitHub&lt;/strong&gt; and walked through &lt;strong&gt;scanning issues&lt;/strong&gt; (seeing what things need doing in a particular project), &lt;strong&gt;forking repositories&lt;/strong&gt; (making a copy of the materials associated with a project) and &lt;strong&gt;making pull requests&lt;/strong&gt; (sending contributions...yes it was all greek to me in the beginning too...and I'm Greek!). Given the short time we had to prepare for the session, the materials provided by Digital Ocean on their &lt;a href="https://hacktoberfest.digitalocean.com/eventkit"&gt;Hacktoberfest event kit page&lt;/a&gt; were an invaluable resource and we can easily recommend them as a great introduction to &lt;strong&gt;contributing to open source&lt;/strong&gt;. Of the 8 folks that made it to the session, 3 would go on to contribute pull requests over the month. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;And a "here's one I made earlier" example pull request from &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mathew_hall?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@mathew_hall&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/BE0Bt5Kszc"&gt;https://t.co/BE0Bt5Kszc&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/XWADfa36e8"&gt;pic.twitter.com/XWADfa36e8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— T D James (@soayipm) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/soayipm/status/915275967593099265?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;October 3, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The sessions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Admittedly, when you work at a computer all day, spending another 3 hours at your screen voluntarily is probably not everyone's top choice. But I personally found the opportunity to carve some time out to explore the huge variety of projects and diverse ways in which to get involved engaging and in some ways quite relaxing. The great collaborative spaces available for booking at the University of Sheffield, the informal setting and hanging out with friends made the sessions something I actually looked forward to. And &lt;strong&gt;the "no pressure" aspect of voluntary contribution meant I was free to play around, follow my own curiosity and explore things I was interested in&lt;/strong&gt; but don't necessarily get the time to work with during my normal working day. Indeed some participants came along to make use of the company and learn some new things not necessarily related to the Hacktoberfest challenge. So &lt;strong&gt;collaboratory, no pressure spaces can be really useful for sharing knowledge.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;2nd &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Sheffield_R_?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@Sheffield_R_&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Hacktoberfest?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#Hacktoberfest&lt;/a&gt; in session!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Featuring &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt; aficionados: &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/soayipm?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@soayipm&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/philmikejones?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@philmikejones&lt;/a&gt;, Maria and Phil! &lt;a href="https://t.co/IRV0dh7rwk"&gt;pic.twitter.com/IRV0dh7rwk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— annakrystalli (@annakrystalli) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/annakrystalli/status/920333953617276933?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;October 17, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Halloween R-stravaganza&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally it was time for the closing event, our &lt;strong&gt;Halloween Hacktoberfest special!&lt;/strong&gt; Excitement was building from the day before when Tamora and I spent the evening carving our &lt;strong&gt;too cute to be scary &lt;code&gt;octocat&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; :heart: &lt;strong&gt;spooky &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; pumpkin!&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;.&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/soayipm?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@soayipm&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; I have been busy! &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;💀👻 &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/github?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@github&lt;/a&gt; 🎃 ready for our &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Sheffield_R_?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@Sheffield_R_&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Hacktoberfest?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#Hacktoberfest&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Halloween?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#Halloween&lt;/a&gt; special! &lt;a href="https://t.co/eyr1LHEj4m"&gt;pic.twitter.com/eyr1LHEj4m&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— annakrystalli (@annakrystalli) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/annakrystalli/status/925137330683416576?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;October 30, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also got some &lt;strong&gt;candy donations from Sheffield RSE&lt;/strong&gt; and a special guest, Raniere Silva (&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/rgaiacs"&gt;\@rgaiacs&lt;/a&gt;), who came all the way from Manchester to join us (although technically it had been his idea after all). The stage was set for a fun finale!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Now is time for &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Hacktoberfest?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#Hacktoberfest&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Halloween?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#Halloween&lt;/a&gt; special. Thanks to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/annakrystalli?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@annakrystalli&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/soayipm?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@soayipm&lt;/a&gt; et al. &lt;a href="https://t.co/WXFjicqbpm"&gt;pic.twitter.com/WXFjicqbpm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Raniere Silva (@rgaiacs) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/rgaiacs/status/925417510404591616?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;October 31, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Success!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we all got our t-shirts I was really impressed with Tamora and Raniere's contributions and their approach served as the biggest take-away for me. They both &lt;strong&gt;focused on a problem or feature that would improve a tool they were already interested in / used&lt;/strong&gt;. They &lt;strong&gt;got feedback on their suggestion before they even begun&lt;/strong&gt; by opening an issue on GitHub and interacting with the project's owners about their idea. That meant their efforts were well focused and much more likely to be accepted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Mission accomplished. :-) Now is time to turn off the laptop and go for trick-or-treat. &lt;a href="https://t.co/eyrlOHnjdg"&gt;pic.twitter.com/eyrlOHnjdg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Raniere Silva (@rgaiacs) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/rgaiacs/status/925433494343385089?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;October 31, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Me too! &lt;a href="https://t.co/3qT4p8wppT"&gt;pic.twitter.com/3qT4p8wppT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— T D James (@soayipm) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/soayipm/status/925449353820540928?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;October 31, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My t-shirt in the end was mainly earned by helping with typos. For Hackoberfest, &lt;em&gt;the size of your contribution doesn't matter&lt;/em&gt; as long as you send a contribution. And finding typos is actually non-trivial and time consuming due to our brain's auto-correct feature. Sadly, the coding pieces that I worked on over the session did not end up making the cut to submit as a functional pull request yet (there'll be a personal blog about my experience during Hacktoberfest coming soon instead). &lt;strong&gt;Mostly however I loved the experience and am already looking forward to organising it next year!&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thinking ahead, 3 things I'd do differently in 2018 would be:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reach out to more organisations:&lt;/strong&gt; There's a great variety of clubs and meetups at the University and more widely in Sheffield that could be interested in joining forces for a Hacktoberfest event. This would give us R users an opportunity to interact with users of other tools and potentially even tackle issues requiring mixed skills as teams.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Start planning earlier!&lt;/strong&gt; This would give us an opportunity to advertise better leading up to the kick-off session and allow us to co-ordinate with other groups. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Run a git &amp;amp; GitHub clinic before the first hack session\:&lt;/strong&gt; This would give the opportunity to folks that have not used GitHub before to get some experience and confidence before turning up to a hack session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;So long #Hactoberfest! See you in 2018!&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pumpkin Carving session and Halloween special powered by:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src="https://embed.spotify.com/?uri=spotify%3Aalbum%3A6gidHRiuT1Aj0HxK7TzAC2" width="300" height="380" frameborder="0" allowtransparency="true"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/sheffieldR-hacktoberfest/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2017 08:09:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>New Group Member: Phil Tooley</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/philtooley_intro/</link><dc:creator>Phil Tooley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am thrilled to have joined the &lt;a href="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/"&gt;Research Software Engineering team at
Sheffield&lt;/a&gt;. My new role is attached to the &lt;a href="https://insigneo.org"&gt;INSIGNEO&lt;/a&gt;
Institute for in silico Medicine here at the University of Sheffield, developing image registration
software as part of the &lt;a href="https://compbiomed.eu"&gt;CompBioMed&lt;/a&gt; project.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;About Me&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/images/ptooley.jpg" align="right"&gt;
I am a former theoretical and computational physicist with particular interests in mathematical
modelling and code optimisation. I am also a stalwart champion of the use of the Scipy stack for
scientific computing, and enjoy trying to make python speed competitive with C and Fortran
(Spoiler alert: it totally can be!) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I am a user of both C(++) and Fortran I find that python is often a better choice for many
tasks even in high performance scientific computing. As well as the huge array of fast mathematical libraries
available to python, it is also possible to write custom routines in pure
(&lt;a href="https://numba.pydata.org"&gt;Numba&lt;/a&gt;) or nearly-pure (&lt;a href="https://cython.org"&gt;Cython&lt;/a&gt;) python
code, and compile them to native machine code.  This can give python equivalent performance to
traditional C or Fortran codes, and opens up the possibility of running python code efficiently
on HPC platforms. (More to come on this topic...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outside the office you will usually find me rock climbing or hiking somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;My previous work&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the last 4 years I have been working on my Ph.D in Theoretical and Computational Plasma Physics
at the &lt;a href="https://strath.ac.uk"&gt;University of Strathclyde&lt;/a&gt; working on novel accelerator technology
known as Laser Wakefield Acceleration (LWFA).  This involves firing a short \((30\,
\mathrm{fs})\) but highly intense \((10^{25}\mathrm{W/m^2})\) laser pulse, into a jet of
helium gas.  The laser ionises the gas to a plasma and drives an electrostatic plasma wave with
intense electric fields which can accelerate electrons to Gigaelectronvolt energies over just a few
mm. (Compared to conventional accelerators such as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SLAC"&gt;SLAC&lt;/a&gt; which
have to be kilometers in length to achieve the same energies.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My research was into methods of controlling and improving the performance of these accelerations,
and relied heavily on &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Particle-in-cell"&gt;Particle in Cell Codes&lt;/a&gt;.
These are massively parallel codes designed to run on HPCs and I spent a lot of my time developing
code extensions and analysis tools for the terabyte scale datasets that they produce.  Typically I
was interested in extracting a very small (usually \(&amp;lt;1\%\) of the total) subset of the electrons
based on some selection criteria. To do this efficiently I developed a custom C++-based analysis
code which can extract electron trajectories from the data based on arbitrary criteria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A major application of LWFAs is as compact sources of X-ray and UV light for imaging and materials
analysis tools in science and industry, and so the second major theme of my work was analysis of the
radiation produced by the accelerated electrons.  This analysis required numerical integrators to
calculate the radiation from the extracted electron trajectories by solving the Liénard-Wiechert
potential equations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>mathjax</category><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/philtooley_intro/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 15:56:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>ATI Data study group</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/ati-data-study-group/</link><dc:creator>Tania A.</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I had the opportunity to attend the &lt;a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/"&gt;Alan Turing Institute (ATI)&lt;/a&gt; Data Study Group (22nd-26th May 2017). The ATI is the national institute for data science and as such, it has strong ties to both academia and industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The event was a week long data hackathon in which multiple groups used their best skills to crack the various projects proposed by the industrial partners. Over 5 days 6 groups worked intensively to deliver feasible solutions to the problems proposed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The projects&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The projects spanned over a wide range of topics, each with their very unique challenges and requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DSTL presented two projects: the first of which was aimed at cyber security, thus trying to identify malicious attacks from IP's traffic data. The second project was focused on the identification of places/geographical landmarks so that the team could predict the likelihood of a given event to take place at a given location.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HSBC's challenge consisted in not the study of a particular data set(s) as the rest of the problems, but was in fact based on the development of a synthetic dataset that could be used along with some algorithms to evaluate the users' behaviour.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Siemens' project was centred around the study of vehicle traffic data that would enable efficient traffic lights and traffic volume control, which would eventually lead to the reduction of carbon emissions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Samsung, being one of the leaders in the smartphones industry decided on using their collected (anonymous) users' data to analyse the users' gaming behaviour (e.g. which games would you biuy/play based on your current gaming habits) as well as developing a gaming recommendation engine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thomson Reuters's challenge was centred around graph analysis. Such a project had as primary goal to identify how positive/negative news of a given company affect other companies/industries within their network and how far does this effect extend.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Hack&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I joined the Thomson Reuters' project as this seemed to be one of the projects with the richest data set, both in its extension and type (e.g news, sentiment analysis, stock market, time series, etc.). The team was formed by 13 people with a huge variety of skills and coming from totally different backgrounds, which is what makes hackathons so exciting. You have to make the most of the skill sets your team has, in a very limited amount of time... pushing you out of your comfort zone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="AT-1" src="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/images/tr.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a brief team introduction our 3 Thomson Reuters facilitators described the data and the challenge in more detail. We then identified the main goals of the project and subdivided the team in about other 4 teams. Once the initial planning was completed, we spent Monday's evening through Wednesday morning learning about their various API's, getting the data, wrangling data... and getting more data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We soon realised that analysing all the data was incredibly complex and of course, there was not one correct way to do it. So we had to reduce the scope of the data we were in fact going to use and the sort of features/phenomena we were interested in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of the Wednesday and Thursday were used to start doing some prediction and regression on the data as well as writing up the report and finishing off our pitch presentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ATI-2" src="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/images/tr2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The findings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certainly, we were able to obtain loads of insight from our data and the various algorithms we used. Some of the most important expected and unexpected findings were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Negative news have a longer impact on the companies involved and those within their network (20 days as opposed to a 4 days impact from the positive news)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The companies are related to each other based on whether their are affiliates, competitors, parents, etc., not surprisingly the competitors are the companies that have the biggest effect on the other companies' stock prices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Different types of industries react differently to negative/positive news and the degree of extension of such an impact varies considerably from one industry type to another&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Taking home&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As every time I have been to a hackathon of some sort I ended up feeling absolutely drained, but accomplished at the same time. Hacks are such a good opportunity to meet like minded people, learn loads of stuff, test yourself, and have fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Would I encourage people to go to one of these events? &lt;strong&gt;Absolutely!&lt;/strong&gt; If you are interested in all things data science you should keep an eye on the future events by the Alan Turing Institute. If you only want to have a go at hacking for fun, for a cause, or to meet new people I would suggest you have a look at the &lt;a href="https://mlh.io"&gt;Major League Hacking&lt;/a&gt;. I am sure you will be able to find something near you and for all sort of interests. Our guys at &lt;a href="https://www.hacksheffield.co"&gt;Hack Sheffield&lt;/a&gt; organise a hackathon once a year so you might want to keep an eye on their activities. For those around Manchester area check out &lt;a href="https://www.hac100.com"&gt;Hac100&lt;/a&gt; including the youth and junior hacks (formerly Hack Manchester).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will the RSE team at the university of Sheffield organise hacks? We have a crazy amount of work on our plates at the moment but we are definitely interested in (co)organising hackathons and many other events throughout the year. So keep your eyes peeled!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/ati-data-study-group/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2017 11:32:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Mozsprint 2017 at the University of Sheffield</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/mozsprint-2017-at-the-university-of-sheffield/</link><dc:creator>Anna Krystalli</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;script&gt;window.twttr = (function(d, s, id) { var js, fjs = d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0], t = window.twttr || {}; if (d.getElementById(id)) return t; js = d.createElement(s); js.id = id; js.src = "https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"; fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js, fjs); t._e = []; t.ready = function(f) { t._e.push(f); }; return t; }(document, "script", "twitter-wjs"));&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;1st-2nd of June 2017&lt;/strong&gt; saw the &lt;strong&gt;Mozilla Global Sprint&lt;/strong&gt; circle
the globe for another time this year. It's Mozilla's flagship two-day
community event, bringing together people from all over the world to
celebrate the power of open collaboration by working on a huge diversity
of community led projects, from developing open source software,
building open tools to writing curriculum, planning events, and more. So
here's a few of my own thoughts and reflections on this year's
happenings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Lead up to the sprint&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Open Leadership Training mentorship&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I joined my first Mozilla Global Sprint last year as the culmination of
the Science Lab’s inaugural &lt;a href="https://science.mozilla.org/blog/wow-introducing-working-open-workshops-and-the-open-leaders-cohort"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Working Open
Workshop&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;strong&gt;mentorship program&lt;/strong&gt;. I worked on my very own open science
project, &lt;a href="https://github.com/annakrystalli/rmacroRDM"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;rmacroRDM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
which I'd spent the lead up to the Sprint preparing for. This year
however it was a different experience for a number of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, the roles have been reversed, and from mentee, I was now a
seasoned open leadership mentor. In fact, I had enjoyed the Open
Leadership training program so much that I’d volunteered to mentor on
the following two rounds, the first culminating at &lt;a href="https://science.mozilla.org/blog/2016-mozfest-recap"&gt;MozFest
2016&lt;/a&gt; and this
latest round at the Global Sprint 2017. Apart from staying connected to
the vibrant network of movers and makers that is
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=quKdaqlR_9w"&gt;Mozilla&lt;/a&gt;, I also found I
got a lot out of mentoring myself. From improving skills in understanding
different people’s styles and support requirements to being introduced
to new ideas, tools and technologies by interesting people from all over
the world! Overall &lt;strong&gt;I find mentorship a positive sum activity for all
parties involved&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the lead up this year involved mentoring two projects while they
prepare to launch at the global sprint. The &lt;strong&gt;Open Leadershp Training
program&lt;/strong&gt; involves mentees working through the &lt;a href="https://mozilla.github.io/open-leadership-training-series/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OLT
materials&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
over 13 weeks while developing the resources required to open their
projects up, ready to receive contributions. On a practical level, the
program teaches approaches to help clearly define and promote the
project and the use of &lt;strong&gt;github as a tool to openly host work on the
web, plan, manage, track, discuss and collaborate.&lt;/strong&gt; But the program
delves deeper into the &lt;strong&gt;very essence of building open, supportive and
welcoming communities&lt;/strong&gt; in which people with an interest in a
tool/cause/idea can contribute what they can, learn and develop
themselves and feel valued and welcome members of a community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weekly contacts with the program alternated between whole cohort vidyo
call check-ins and more focused one-on-one skype calls between mentors
and mentees. This round I co-mentored with the wonderful &lt;a href="https://www.newamerica.org/our-people/chris-ritzo/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chris
Ritzo&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="https://www.newamerica.org/oti/"&gt;New
America’s Open Technologiy Institute&lt;/a&gt;
and we took on two extremely exciting projects, &lt;strong&gt;Aletheia&lt;/strong&gt; and
&lt;strong&gt;Teach-R&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mentee projects:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/600/0*5h4_CqTJrsVgcTka.png" width="100px"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Headed up by &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/kade-morton-34179283/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kade
Morton&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
(&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/cypath"&gt;@cypath&lt;/a&gt;), a super sharp, super visionary,
super motivated, self-described crypto nerd from Brisbane, Australia,
&lt;a href="https://github.com/aletheia-foundation/aletheia-admin"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aletheia&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
doesn't pull any punches when describing it's reason for being:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/annakrystalli/random_repo/master/images/aletheia.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In response they're building a decentralised and distributed database as
a publishing platform for scientific research, leveraging two key pieces
of technology, IPFS and blockchain. Many of the technical details are
frankly over my head but I nonetheless learned a lot from Kade’s
meticulous preparation and drive. Read more about the ideas behind the
project
&lt;a href="https://medium.com/read-write-participate/aletheia-11aebe18f490"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/600/0*H7u7_YDO9xJ5yVTJ.png" width="140px"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What can I say about &lt;a href="https://marcosvital.wordpress.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marcos
Vital&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, professor of Quantitative
Ecology at Federal University of Alagoas (UFAL), Brazil and fellow
#rstats aficionado apart from he is also a huge inspiration! An
effortless community builder, he runs a very successful local &lt;a href="https://marcosvital.github.io/studyGroup/"&gt;study
group&lt;/a&gt; and has built a
popular and engaged online community through his lab
&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/leq.ufal/"&gt;facebook&lt;/a&gt; page promoting science
communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The topic of his project
&lt;a href="https://github.com/marcosvital/teach-R-project"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Teach-R&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is close
to my heart, aiming to collate and develop training materials to
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;TEACH&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; people to &lt;strong&gt;TEACH&lt;/strong&gt; R. Read more about it
&lt;a href="https://medium.com/read-write-participate/the-open-teach-r-project-d87b9240f51a"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Hosting a Sheffield site.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, this year I helped host a site here at the &lt;a href="https://ti.to/Mozilla/global-sprint-sheffield"&gt;University of
Sheffield&lt;/a&gt;, and seeing as
the sprint coincided with my first day as a &lt;a href="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/contact/"&gt;Research Software Engineer
for Sheffield RSE&lt;/a&gt;, we decided to take
the event under our wing. With space secured and swag and coffee funds
supplied by the Science Lab, the local site was read for action!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;
&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;
Want to get your paws on some this
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/MozillaScience"&gt;@MozillaScience&lt;/a&gt; swag?
Join us at the
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/RSE_Sheffield"&gt;@RSE_Sheffield&lt;/a&gt; hosted
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/mozsprint?src=hash"&gt;\#mozsprint&lt;/a&gt;
site! &lt;a href="https://t.co/FvN88psLbh"&gt;https://t.co/FvN88psLbh&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://t.co/ELHJdJNBWZ"&gt;pic.twitter.com/ELHJdJNBWZ&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
— annakrystalli (@annakrystalli)
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/annakrystalli/status/868068698518585344"&gt;May
26, 2017&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Sprint!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Sprint at the University of Sheffield.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The was a good buzz of activity throughout the sprint at the site, with
a few core participants while others came and went as they could. At the
very least, roaming participants managed to soak up some of the
atmosphere and pick up some git and github skills,...a success in my
books!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stuart Mumford (&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/StuartMumford"&gt;@StuartMumford&lt;/a&gt;) led
project &lt;a href="https://www.mozillapulse.org/entry/226"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SunPy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a python
based open-source solar data analysis environment and attracted a number
of local contributors, including a new PhD student, although, as is
often the case, much of the first morning seemed to be spent battling
python installation on his laptop! Worth it for picking up a local
contributor that will hopefully remain engaged throughout his studies
though, and the team managed to push on with bug fixes and documentation
development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jez Cope (&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jezcope"&gt;@jezcope&lt;/a&gt;), our University's
Research Data Manager was contributing to &lt;a href="https://librarycarpentry.github.io/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Library
Carpentry&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, one of the biggest and
most popular projects at his year's Sprint and also brought super tasty
banana bread. He's also blogged about his experiences
&lt;a href="https://erambler.co.uk/blog/mozilla-global-sprint-2017/?utm_content=buffer35502&amp;amp;utm_medium=social&amp;amp;utm_source=twitter.com&amp;amp;utm_campaign=buffer"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Myself, while of course tempted by the many R, open science and
reproducibility projects on offer, in the end chose to work on something
unrelated to what I'm lucky to do for work and focus on a project I'm
interested in personally. So I teamed up with Tyler Kolody
(&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/TyTheSciGuy"&gt;@TyTheSciGuy&lt;/a&gt;) on his timely project
&lt;a href="https://github.com/TyJK/EchoBurst"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EchoBurst&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The project aims to
address our growing, social media facilitated, retreat into echo
chambers, which is resulting in increasingly polarised public discourse
and an unwillingness to engage with views we disagree with. The idea is
to attempt to &lt;a href="https://medium.com/read-write-participate/echoburst-77b3aa661d52"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;burst through such bubbles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, by developing a browser
extension with the potential to distinguish toxic content, more likely
to shut down discussion, from more constructive content that might be
able to bridge different perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Admittedly the project is very ambitious with a long way to go, many
stages and various techniques/technologies to incorporate including
natural language processing, building the browser plugin and even
considering psychological and behavioural aspects in designing how to
present information that might oppose a user's view without triggering
the &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/srep39589"&gt;natural shut-down
response&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was plenty of really interesting brainstrorming discussion but the
biggest initial challenge, and where the project could use the most
help, is in collecting training data. The main approach is for
contributors to help collect URLs of blogs on &lt;a href="https://github.com/TyJK/EchoBurst/issues/4"&gt;polarising
topics&lt;/a&gt; from which to
&lt;a href="https://github.com/TyJK/EchoBurst/issues/9"&gt;scrape content&lt;/a&gt;. But during
the sprint we also added the option for contributors to add relevant
youtube videos to &lt;a href="https://github.com/TyJK/EchoBurst/blob/master/Youtube%20Caption%20Dump/Instructions.md"&gt;collaborative
playlists&lt;/a&gt;.
We also started working on simple R functions to help scrape and clean
the caption content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Sprint across the globe&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What a productive event this year's sprint was! While details of the
level of activity have been
&lt;a href="https://medium.com/read-write-participate/48-hours-devoted-to-a-healthier-internet-c3e1d03cf5aa"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;covered&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
and
&lt;a href="https://storify.com/MozillaScience/2017-mozilla-global-sprint"&gt;storyfied&lt;/a&gt;
elsewhere and the final project demos can be found
&lt;a href="https://public.etherpad-mozilla.org/p/mozsprint-2017-demos-jun-6"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
and
&lt;a href="https://public.etherpad-mozilla.org/p/mozsprint-2017-demos-jun-7"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;,
I just wanted to highlight some basic stats:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Global #mozprint involved:&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;65&lt;/strong&gt; sites (+ virtual participants)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;20&lt;/strong&gt; countries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;108&lt;/strong&gt; projects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;During the 50 hour #mozsprint, we saw:&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;302&lt;/strong&gt; pull requests closed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;320&lt;/strong&gt; pull requests opened&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2223&lt;/strong&gt; comments &amp;amp; issues&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;824&lt;/strong&gt; commits pushed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*75Nv4-7XCOcnjA9PRjt9sA.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BOOM!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(access the full data on github activity&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;a href="https://medium.com/read-write-participate/mozsprint-by-the-github-numbers-49d518551725"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;here&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Mentee progress&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was really happy to see both our mentees get great responses, pick up
new contributors and make good progress on their projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marcos expertly moderated a &lt;a href="https://gitter.im/teach-R-project/Lobby"&gt;very active gitter
    channel&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;strong&gt;Teach-R&lt;/strong&gt;,
    attracted a number of excellent and very engaged new contributors,
    adding a number of new lessons, &lt;strong&gt;in both&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;a href="https://github.com/marcosvital/teach-R-project/tree/master/courses/en"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;English&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;a href="https://github.com/marcosvital/teach-R-project/tree/master/courses/pt"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Portuguese&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;!&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kade also got great engagement for &lt;strong&gt;Aletheia&lt;/strong&gt;, including
    onboarding science communicator Lisa Mattias
    (&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/l_matthia"&gt;@l_matthia&lt;/a&gt;), who's already
    &lt;a href="http://www.wherethereislight.net/aletheia-for-osfair2017/"&gt;blogged
    about&lt;/a&gt;
    their plans to take the project forward by applying to present it at
    this year's &lt;a href="http://www.opensciencefair.eu/"&gt;Open Science Fair&lt;/a&gt;.
    Importantly, he also managed to attract the javascipt developer
    they've been desperately looking for. Success! You can read more
    about Kade's experiences of the sprint
    &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/aletheia-mozilla-global-sprint-2017-kade-morton?trk=v-feed&amp;amp;lipi=urn%3Ali%3Apage%3Ad_flagship3_detail_base%3BVDNGKz72yDQY9IDHaKn6gg%3D%3D"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;They both made us very proud indeed!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Highlights&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the most important feature of the sprint for me every year is the
global comradery and atmosphere of celebration. Handing off from one
timezone to the other and checking in within our own to &lt;a href="https://public.etherpad-mozilla.org/p/sciencelab-2017globalsprint"&gt;hear from
leads&lt;/a&gt;
about their project needs and progress, hanging out with participants
from far and wide on vidyo and through &lt;a href="https://gitter.im/mozilla/global-sprint-2017?utm_source=share-link&amp;amp;utm_medium=link&amp;amp;utm_campaign=share-link"&gt;streams of constant messaging on
gitter&lt;/a&gt;,
catching up with friends across the network...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;
&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/h3x1t"&gt;@h3x1t&lt;/a&gt; is hosting
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/mozsprint?src=hash"&gt;\#mozsprint&lt;/a&gt;
2017 :)&lt;br&gt;More photos are coming :)
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/HEXit?src=hash"&gt;\#HEXit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/MozSylhet?src=hash"&gt;\#MozSylhet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/MozillaSylhet?src=hash"&gt;\#MozillaSylhet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/SprintBangladesh?src=hash"&gt;\#SprintBangladesh&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://t.co/ZK4OnAwPiq"&gt;pic.twitter.com/ZK4OnAwPiq&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
— S. O. F. Towaha (@SOFTowaha)
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/SOFTowaha/status/870226482223763456"&gt;June
1, 2017&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;...and cake...sooooooooo much cake!!&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;
&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;
This year's
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/mozcake?src=hash"&gt;\#mozcake&lt;/a&gt; - a
6-storey Black Forest cake. We are going to 'hack' into it shortly ;-)
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/lc2017?src=hash"&gt;\#lc2017&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://t.co/Cz9yAmcnOi"&gt;pic.twitter.com/Cz9yAmcnOi&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
— Belinda Weaver (@cloudaus)
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/cloudaus/status/870051564563578881"&gt;May 31,
2017&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;disclaimer: this cake was sadly not at the Sheffield site. It
definitely has inspired me to put a lot more effort into this aspect of
the sprint next year though!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The end of the sprint is always a bit sad but the &lt;strong&gt;projects live on&lt;/strong&gt;,
hopefully with a new lease of life. So if, by reading this, you're
&lt;a href="https://mozilla.github.io/global-sprint/participants/"&gt;inspired to
contribute&lt;/a&gt;,
check out the &lt;a href="https://mozilla.github.io/global-sprint/projects/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;full list of
projects&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for
something that might appeal. There's a huge diversity of topics, tasks
and skills required to chose from and fun new people to meet!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So does the network&lt;/strong&gt; so if you’ve got an exciting idea of your own
that you think would make a good open source project make sure to check
out &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/MozOpenLeaders"&gt;@MozOpenLeaders&lt;/a&gt; and look out
for the next mentorship round.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the impact on Sheffield RSE, well there was one point where we
managed to get the full team and loose collaborators working in one room
(we’re normally spread out across the university). It felt great to work
together from the same space so we decided to make a point of routinely
booking one of the many excellent co-working spaces the University of
Sheffield has on offer and establish regular &lt;strong&gt;work-together&lt;/strong&gt; days!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;So thanks for the inspiration and excellent times Mozilla! Till the next time!&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(ie &lt;a href="https://mozillafestival.org/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mozfest 2017&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Sounds:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from the coffee and good vibes, the day was also fuelled by
sounds. Here's a couple of the mixes that kept the Sheffield site going!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Grooves no. 1:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;iframe width="100%" height="166" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/290950663&amp;amp;color=ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false"&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Grooves no. 2:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;iframe width="100%" height="166" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/321722836&amp;amp;color=ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false"&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/mozsprint-2017-at-the-university-of-sheffield/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jun 2017 10:56:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>