<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>RSE at Sheffield (Posts by Twin Karmakharm)</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/authors/twin-karmakharm.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Jun 2018 17:11:43 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>RSE Computing Seminar and Coffee &amp; Cake event 19th June 2018 at 12:00</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/2018-06-19-rse-computing-seminar-coffe-cake/</link><dc:creator>Twin Karmakharm</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Both events will be held at COM-G12-Main Lewin, Computer Science Department (ground floor) on the 19th of June, starting from 12:00&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;12:00 - RSE Seminar: Tackling the learning curve of scientific programming&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By: Dr. Patricio Ortiz&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Talk Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Programming is part of the curriculum of students of computer science, and it will be complemented with other related subjects to make them knowledgeable on the subject. The situation of a science or engineering student is the opposite; typically they have one course to learn one language, and that language is usually not the one they will first face in real-life situations. This situation has occurred for decades, and it is likely not going to change, but there is a real need to better prepare science and engineering students to face the very steep learning curve of having to start programming as part of an ongoing project or their thesis.
Universities like ours offer excellent facilities like the HPCs supplied by CICS, yet the reality is that many students and young researchers may have never used a Unix based system, let alone a parallel system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book I wrote, "first steps in scientific programmings" aims at facilitating the passage through the learning curve by providing tips based on years of experience and my interaction with students and brilliant young researchers who did not have the opportunity to learn anywhere else the challenges which programming in a scientific environment involve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will briefly describe the points which I think are more important to emphasise, points which I've confirmed as important by interacting with other experienced researchers at the U. of Sheffield, who are trying to provide support for the people starting in this field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Link for the book:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://sites.google.com/view/fsscientificprogramming/home"&gt;https://sites.google.com/view/fsscientificprogramming/home&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A supportive link:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://sites.google.com/a/sheffield.ac.uk/rcg/my-blog/research-computing-notes/firststepsinscientificprogramming"&gt;https://sites.google.com/a/sheffield.ac.uk/rcg/my-blog/research-computing-notes/firststepsinscientificprogramming&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please Register using &lt;a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/tackling-the-learning-curve-of-scientific-programming-tickets-46366639868"&gt;Eventbrite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;13:00 - Coffee and Cake event&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Coffe and Cake event is open to everyone and offers a great opportunity to further discuss the topics raised by our speaker. In addition, if you have any particular research software issues or would like to have a general discussion about research software or software in teaching, please come along for an informal chat with the RSE team.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>seminar event</category><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/2018-06-19-rse-computing-seminar-coffe-cake/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 31 May 2018 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Coffee and Cakes Event</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/coffee-and-cakes-event-2nd-after/</link><dc:creator>Twin Karmakharm</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The RSE Sheffield team would like to thank everyone for attending the second Coffee and Cakes Event that was held last Wednesday (31/05/2017). The event provided a great opportunity to hear from researchers all around the University about the software engineering challenges faced within their projects. We hope to use the insights gained from the event to help improve your research workflow in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To get updates on future RSE events, please join our&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://groups.google.com/a/sheffield.ac.uk/forum/#!forum/gpucomputing"&gt;RSE Google Discussion Group&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/coffee-and-cakes-event-2nd-after/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2017 14:12:12 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>First GPU Computing Seminar - Towards achieving GPU-native adaptive mesh refinement</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/2nd-gpu-seminar-amr/</link><dc:creator>Twin Karmakharm</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="amr" src="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/images/2017_05_30_gpu_seminar_amr.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've kicked off our first GPU Computing group seminar this year with a talk by &lt;strong&gt;Ania Brown&lt;/strong&gt; from Oxford e-Research Centre titled &lt;strong&gt;"Towards achieving GPU-native adaptive mesh refinement"&lt;/strong&gt; on 30th of May 2017. Adaptive mesh refinement (AMR) is a method for reducing memory cost by varying the accuracy in each region to match the physical characteristics of the simulation, at the cost of increased data structure complexity. Ania described the optimisation and software challenges that need to be considered when implementing AMR on GPUs, based on her experience working on a GPU-native framework for stencil calculations on a tree-based adaptively refined mesh as part of her Master degree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's no offical GPU Computing talks in June but we highly recommend the upcoming talk &lt;strong&gt;"From Democratic Consensus to Cannibalistic Hordes: The Principles of Collective Animal Behaviour"&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;strong&gt;Prof. Iain Couzin&lt;/strong&gt; on the &lt;strong&gt;29th of June 2017&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Links and More Information&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For presentation slides and more information on both of these talks, visit the &lt;a href="http://gpucomputing.shef.ac.uk/seminars/"&gt;GPU Computing seminars&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/2nd-gpu-seminar-amr/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2017 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>